<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The good order of truth justified wherein our womens meetings and order of marriage (by some more especially opposed) are proved agreeable to Scripture and sound reason / by an old and true friend to liberty of conscience, but not to disorder, William Loddington.</title>
            <author>Loddington, William, 1626?-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21478</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12406291</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12406291</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61406</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61406)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 767:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good order of truth justified wherein our womens meetings and order of marriage (by some more especially opposed) are proved agreeable to Scripture and sound reason / by an old and true friend to liberty of conscience, but not to disorder, William Loddington.</title>
                  <author>Loddington, William, 1626?-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Andrew Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Quaker women.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61406:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Good Order OF TRUTH JUSTIFIED; Wherein our <hi>Womens Meetings</hi> and <hi>Order of Marriage</hi> (by ſome more eſpecially oppoſed) are proved agreeable to Scripture and Sound REASON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By an old and true Friend to</hi> Liberty of Conſcience, <hi>but not to</hi> Diſorder, <hi>William Loddington.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Formality, not Form, feeds the Spirit of Perſecution.</q>
            <q>So the Service of the Houſe of the Lord was ſet in Order, <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 29.35.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Though I be abſent in the Fleſh, yet am I with you in Spirit, joying and beholding your Order, and the ſtedfaſtneſs of your Faith in Chriſt, <bibl>
                  <hi>Col. 2.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed and Sold by <hi>Andrew Sowle,</hi> in <hi>Holloway-Lane,</hi> in <hi>Shoreditch,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:61406:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61406:2"/>
            <head>The Good Order OF TRUTH JUSTIFIED.</head>
            <p>UNITY in Spirit is the true and firm Foundation of Love and Fellowſhip: All <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> and <hi>Conformity</hi> not ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from this, is but Hypocriſie. Where there is Unity in the Life and Spirit of Chriſt, there will be Uniformity (if no Temptation hinder) in the viſible Life and Order, anſwerable to the meaſure received. Do men gather Grapes, or Grape Leaves of Thorns? The Sap puts forth the ſame Leaf as well as Fruit, in every Branch. Yet the compariſon holds no further than to the faithful, becauſe Men may counterfeit, but Trees cannot.</p>
            <p>Outward appearances beget a Name, as to outward Fellowſhips: He ſhall by men of the World be reputed a <hi>Quaker,</hi> that is conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Language and Geſture; but the true <hi>Quaker</hi> (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true <hi>Chriſtian</hi>) takes his Meaſures from better Foundations. There are Vertues, Behaviours or Operations of mens Spirits diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable to the Spiritual, more or leſs, and according as they feel Unity in theſe, they joyn together to exalt his Glory, who brought them to a ſence of Life Immortal, into which the Hypocrite cannot enter; though from this men may fall.</p>
            <p>Never more need to watch and pray, that we be not deceived; for Truth was never more lively counterfeited; nor never did the Myſtery of Iniquity work more plauſibly to break <hi>Sion's</hi> Peace. What more hated than <hi>Impoſition?</hi> What more nauſeous than <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality?</hi> What more ridiculous than <hi>impertinent Ceremony?</hi> The Serpent knowing all this, covers himſelf in ſome places with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61406:3"/>for <hi>Moderation</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> as it were in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to all <hi>Impoſition,</hi> when indeed its to bring in Bondage to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: But the Daughter of <hi>Babylon</hi> is known, though decked with Pearls and fine Array, glorious words of Truth.</p>
            <p>This Spirit never had a fairer advantage, becauſe ſo many have turned Perſecutors under pretences of Conformity to Religious Order and Government; ſo that many Arguments now brought in behalf of good Order, though ſound and rational, yet are ſlighted, becauſe formerly ſome Perſecutors have made uſe of them to a wrong end. Hence ſtrong Deluſions get over ſuch as receive not the Love of Truth, that they may be ſaved. Yea, ſome who I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve did in love receive it, yet not keeping to it, are drawn into oppoſition to its Order; whereby Diviſions and Offences ariſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the peaceable Doctrine of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>Two things are principally pretended to be the ſubjects of their Diſſatisfaction, <hi>viz.</hi> our <hi>Womens Meetings,</hi> and <hi>Order of Marriage.</hi> But alas! if theſe two things were removed, other Diſſatisfactions would ſpring up, and others after them, till and Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were diſſolved. They know not what Spirit it is which makes them ſtumble; give it an Inch, and it will take more: Nay, ſome have even loſt all their Profeſſion of Religion by doing ſo.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe I am verily perſwaded in my own Spirit, that good Words and fair Speeches deceive many ſimple hearts, I feel a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for their ſakes, (ſome are ſo far gone, pure Reaſon doth not reach them) to write ſomething of what the Lord, not man, nor by Man, opened to me about theſe matters, that after my ſearching and trying them, I might be eſtabliſhed (glory to his Name) in his bleſſed Truth, and enabled in ſome meaſure to give a Reaſon of my Hope and Practice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>Firſt</hi> then, this Queſtion, in my Underſtanding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the whole matter.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whether it be agreeable to Scripture for our Women Friends to meet by themſelves, or to ſit, ſpeak and act equally with men in Meetings of Buſineſs of an outward or temporal nature or tendency?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I put Scripture in the Queſtion, becauſe I know its a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Objection, <hi>That Womens Meetings are not to be found there.</hi> Is not this plain limiting the Spirit of the Lord to thoſe only times when that was written, as if nothing of Order hereafter may or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61406:3"/>muſt be neceſſary and expedient, but what was ſo in thoſe days? There is a general Rule (not the worſe becauſe Superſtition hath abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it) in 1 Cor. 14. <hi>That all things be done Decently, and in Order;</hi> but the particular Circumſtances of Decency and Order are left to the judgment of Chriſtians in every Age, a the Lord ſhall direct them. But to come cloſer to the Queſtion, its very clear to me, that our Womens Meetings are plainly agreeable to the ſcope and fence of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in 1 Cor. 13.3. where he weightily argues, and earneſtly preſſeth us to take notice of it, ſaying, <hi>I would have you to know, That the Head of the Woman is the Man.</hi> If ſo, then if our Womens Meetings conſiſt with the Headſhip, they are juſtified by this Scripture; but ſuch Meetings as are deſtructive to it, and take it away, cannot be lawful.</p>
            <p>That the firſt are conſiſtent with this Headſhip, and the other deſtructive, appears by what follows.</p>
            <p>If Women be taken into Mens Meetings, appointed for outward or temporal Concerns, with equal freedom to ſit, ſpeak and act with them, then I ſee no Headſhip man hath: For if he hath any, it muſt be either in Temporal or Spiritual matters. In Spirituals he hath none, for the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. affirms, <hi>That Male and Female are all one in Chriſt;</hi> that is, in ſervices purely ſpiritual, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting only to Chriſt and the Soul; ſuch as Prayer and Prophecy; Therefore in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. equal freedom is given to the Woman as much as to the Man to Pray and Prophecy.</p>
            <p>But on the other hand, Women Friends meeting by themſelves, may without the leaſt ſuſpition of uſurping Authority over the Men, confer and reaſon together, how to ſerve Truth in their places, in ſuch things as are moſt proper and ſuitable for them, ſtill ſubmitting to the Wiſdom of God in the Mens Meetings: Whereas being mixed together, if a man ſhould make a motion about any buſineſs, and a Woman ſhould ſtand up, and ſignifie her diſlike of it, though in moſt mild and tender words, would not any Man, yea, an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believer (if he ſhould come in and hear it) would he not conclude the Women in ſuch Meetings had as much Power as the Men? Let none Reply, <hi>It matters not what <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers ſay;</hi> for <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf was very careful that nothing might be done in the Church of Chriſt, that might ſtumble Unbelievers, as hereafter will be noted, from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. Wherefore he knowing Man's Headſhip to be owned by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61406:4"/>the Law of Nature, commands the VVoman to be covered when ſhe prayes or prophecies; which Covering, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. is called, <hi>Power on her Head,</hi> becauſe it was to ſignifie to all that ſhould come into the Meeting, that though she had equal freedom with Man to pray or prophecy, yet nevertheleſs ſhe ſtill was to own, and did own the Man's Power over her in viſible or temporal things. But the Man praying or prophecying, is to be uncovered, in teſtimony that there is no Power in any Creature above him. And to anſwer all Objections, in eaſe this his Epiſtle should come where People did wear no Coverings on their Heads, then he directs them to Nature's covering to confirm this Headship: <hi>The Womans Hair</hi> (ſaith he, verſ. 15.) <hi>is given her for a Covering, and ſhe is not to cut it off,</hi> nor the Man's to be worm of a length like the Womans; for that would be a ſhame in Nature, verſ. 14. for it would ſignifie he hath loſt his Headſhip.</p>
            <p>Thus we may obſerve how zealous the Apoſtle is in this matter; there was no need to write this to diſtinguiſh their Sex, for that was as plainly manifeſt by their other Garments, in thoſe days as well as ours.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Headſhip</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> over the <hi>Woman,</hi> being only in Temporals, hinders not their Spiritual Unity: So the Headſhip of God men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſame Verſe, takes not away the Unity of God and Chriſt. Jeſus himſelf rightly divides this word of Truth; for in <hi>John</hi> 10.29. ſpeaking of his ſpiritual Power to ſave his Sheep, he ſaith, <hi>I and my Father are one:</hi> But in chap. 14.28. relating to the concerns and ſufferings of his Body, then he ſaith, <hi>My Father <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s greater than I.</hi> So Male and Female are all one in Chriſt, that is, in Spirituals, but Man the Head in Temporals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> If any reply, <hi>This Headſhip is only to be underſtood in Family Affairs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ</hi> In granting this they grant the other alſo, unleſs they will ſay, Man is Head in ſome ſmall private Concerns, but in publick and weighty matters the Woman is to be his equal in Power. This renders the Apoſtle very weak in writing ſo earneſtly for ſo ſmall a matter, which indeed requires no Proof at all. But further, if this Objection were true, then theſe Geſtures of covering and uncover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Head, before commanded, ſhould only be uſed in private Family Prayer or Prophecy, where the Headſhip thereby ſignified, is only to be in force.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61406:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. But I have heard it hinted, <hi>That Women might be with Men in Meetings of Buſineſs, provided they were ſilent, as if they were in ſuch Meeting the Apoſtle relates to, when he commands Women to be ſilent,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.25. and 1 Tim. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then muſt they ſit as uſeleſs Spectators, not daring to ſpeak what may open in their Underſtandings, touching any thing among them. But a little to explain theſe Scriptures; there is not the leaſt ground to ſuppoſe the Apoſtle diverted his Mind from Meetings of Worſhip to Meetings of Buſineſs, when he ſaid, <hi>Let the Women be ſilent:</hi> for in this 14th chapter, he writing principally about <hi>Prophecy,</hi> recommends ſome Circumſtances neceſſary to be obſerved, which he would have every man, that thinks himſelf to be a Prophet, or Spiritual, to own as Gods commands, <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. Two Scandals he labours to prevent. 1ſt. <hi>When any ſpeak with</hi> Tongues (which he would not forbid, though he commends Prophecying in plain known Language before it) <hi>that there ſhould be an Interpreter ready, or elſe it were better to be ſilent,</hi> verſ. 28. and the Reaſon is in v. 23. <hi>Becauſe if an unlearned Man, or an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliever ſhould come in, he would ſay they were Mad.</hi> Mark how careful he is of Truth's Honour, that Unbelievers Mouthes might not be opened againſt it. And, <hi>2dly,</hi> he commands, <hi>That Women ſhould then be ſilent;</hi> that is, when any ſpeak with Tongues above their Underſtanding, it is not permitted unto them to ſpeak in the Church; that is, by way of asking Queſtions there: <hi>But if they will learn</hi> (ſaith he) that is, if they have a deſire to know the meaning of any thing there ſpoken in a Tongue unknown to them, <hi>let them ask</hi> [Mark, ask]<hi>at home:</hi> For if a Woman ſhould but ask, or deſire a Man in the Church to explain himſelf, it might be apt to be taken for a Command by Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, if they ſhould come in; and ſo that might occaſion ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scandal, <hi>That Chriſtian Women did uſurp Authority over the Men.</hi> Wherefore writing to <hi>Timothy,</hi> he requires the ſame thing to be obſerved by the Women there, telling him, <hi>That they were to learn in ſilence with all Subjection or Quietneſs,</hi> and not to teach or ſpeak in any ſuch way as might look like uſurping Authority over the Men, either in the Church, or indeed in any other place; for that would ſtumble even Unbelievers they could not endure that. And ſo he gives two Reaſons why Man is to have this Headſhip; <hi>Becauſe</hi> Adam <hi>was firſt formed,</hi> v. 13. Secondly, <hi>Becauſe</hi> Adam <hi>was not deceived,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:61406:5"/>(that is, by the Serpent) <hi>but the Woman being deceived, was in the Tranſgreſſion,</hi> v. 14. And this in ſhort is the plain ſence and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of theſe two Scriptures compared together, which are ſo often miſ-applyed to wrong ends and practices this day. But now, all this doth not forbid a Womens oppoſing a wrong Spirit, if it ſhall dare to ſpeak in the Church; Woman or Child, as well as Man, in the movings of the Spirit of God may do that; Nor doth it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid a Womans Praying or Prophecying; for then he had contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted what (in chap. 11. of the ſame Epiſtle) he allowed of. Thus the Scripture, ſo plainly aſſerting Man's Headſhip, by true conſequence, condemns all Practices that overthrow it. And truly, I often admire, that ſome whom I know to be ingenious and rational in other things, ſhould not ſee how they cloud themſelves at preſent, nor foreſee the future Inconveniences of ſuch Meetings they contend for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. I once heard a kind of arguing againſt this Headſhip, from the ſtate of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> before the fall, <hi>As if Truth's Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples did lead us to joyn Man and Woman together now, in ordering all things as they two did in Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I own, Truth preſſeth to that Perfection in Spirit: <hi>He that is in Chriſt is a new Creature,</hi> as to the ſpiritual part, being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into that Spirit which knows no diſtinctions, according to Fleſh, as of <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Greek, Bond</hi> or <hi>Free, Male</hi> or <hi>Female.</hi> But to turn this into an Argument for outward things; and to ſay, if any one be in Chriſt, his outward Body is a new Creature, not of the ſame Fleſh and Bones, nor liable to the ſame Diſtempers as before; and ſo to make void all diſtinction in the natural Sex, States and Conditions, is great Darkneſs, and contains ſuch Abſurdities as run all into Confuſion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more to this particular: There is more light in one Sun than in many Stars. Until this Principle of <hi>Man's Headſhip</hi> in Temporal things be diſſanulled, I know nothing can be urged in oppoſition to the Order of our Womens Meetings, or in behalf of the mixed Meetings before mentioned.</p>
            <p>The Second thing in the Order of Truth, by ſome oppoſed, is <hi>Our way of Marriage;</hi> which though eſtabliſhed by the Wiſdom of God in our Meetings, being comely and commendable, even in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61406:5"/>the Eyes of ſober diſcreet People of the World; yet ſome profeſſing Truth, (A Shame to ſee it!) are ſo pettiſh and conceited, that nothing will pleaſe them, unleſs a liberty be granted to Marry what way, yea, and what Perſons too they pleaſe. And except we will conſent to, and approve of ſuch a Liberty, they cry out, <hi>Impoſition, Formality, &amp;c.</hi> And they are very ready to urge the Apoſtles granting liberty of eating <hi>Herbs</hi> and <hi>Fleſh, Rom.</hi> 14. as a good Argument for them. Is Marriage of no greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern than ſuch things? According to my meaſure in Truth, I affirm, they may more plauſibly contend for a liberty to put off their Hats in Saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as the World doth; for this would not ſo much reflect upon Truth as diverſity of Marriages: The World doth not regard our Geſtures or Salutations, as matters of Religion; but <hi>Marriage</hi> is generally owned to be Gods Ordinance: Wherefore if our Meetings, (which we believe have greater light in Religious matters than other gatherings) ſhould not agree in the manner of celebrating this Ordinance of God, would they not render themſelves very weak, yea, below the Wiſdom of other Churches (ſo called?) Will the <hi>Jew</hi> tolerate his <hi>Circumciſion?</hi> the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, Water-Baptiſm?</hi> or the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> their <hi>Matrimony</hi> to be adminiſtred after divers ways and different forms? Do not we truly conclude againſt all them who contend for <hi>Water-Baptiſm,</hi> that they are all in the dark about it, becauſe they cannot agree either as to the ſubject, or to the manner of its Adminiſtration? And would they not ſay the ſame of us, if we ſhould fall into the like Controverſie? But bleſſed be God, a Remnant are kept by his Power over all theſe vain janglings and Oppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Theſe Hearts are knit together in Love and Peace by his Spirit; and they ſtrive together, and are ſtrengthened by his Might to hold faſt the Faith and Order of his bleſſed Truth.</p>
            <p>But the great ſcruple is, <hi>Propounding Intentions of Marriage to the Womens Meetings;</hi> and no other Reaſon for it, as I remember, <hi>but that it was Needleſs.</hi>—A few words to this.</p>
            <p>If one principal end of publiſhing Intentions of Marriage, is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Abuſes, and to diſcover deceit in either Party, if there be any, then all means very ſerviceable to this end, ought not to be accounted need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs: But our Womens Meetings have been very ſerviceable to this end. —Therefore I know not which part of this Argument can be deny'd. If it be queried in contempt of them, <hi>What Service have they done, which might not as well have been done by the men? Anſ.</hi> This is a groſs Reflections take heed of it. Its all one as to ſay, A <hi>Man</hi> might have ſlain <hi>Siſera,</hi> as well as <hi>Jac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, Judg.</hi> 4.22. A <hi>Man</hi> might have directed <hi>Naaman</hi> to the Prophet, as well as the <hi>little Maid,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5. <hi>Men</hi> might have brought
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61406:6"/>the Tidings of the Reſurrection of Jeſus, as well as the <hi>Women, Matth.</hi> 28. But who art thou that replyeſt againſt Gods Inſtruments? Many Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might be given, of later date than the Scriptures, of Gods making <hi>Women</hi> ſerviceable in divers things of this Nature. Therefore ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ſharp Rebuke, as would put Women out of all Service in the Church, and confine them to their Houſhold Affairs, which I fear is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Bottom and Root of the Scruple.</p>
            <p>If it be replyed, <hi>That theſe Services I inſtance were done by particular private Women, and not by Womens Meetings; and that they could freely tell their Intention of Marriage to any particular Women, but not to a Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then the ſcruple falls upon them as a Meeting. Then the Queſtion will be, Whether their Act only of coming together be diſliked, or their Buſineſs? The firſt is proved before, and the other muſt needs be approved by theſe Inſtances laſt mentioned. For if the Scripture te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, <hi>That God hath often bleſſed the Advice and Instructions of particular Women,</hi> much more Reaſon have we to expect and hope for good Advice, and Aſſiſtance from them, in matters propounded to them, when they are ſolemnly met to wait upon the Lord for Wiſdom and Counſel in things committed to their care. For there is an abſolute Promiſe of <hi>Gods Preſence to two or three met in his Name,</hi> Mat. 18.22. Who dare ſay, this was made only to men? Much might be written upon this very Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But I love both hearing and ſpeaking few words, and they (in diſputable caſes eſpecially) as cloſe to the point as poſſible.</p>
            <p>Now I am writing about the form of Godlineſs, I feel it neceſſary to add a little to prevent the fears that may enter, leſt ſome who contend for Form, loſe Power, and turn Perſecutors, as others have done, for their Forms, when got into temporal Power and Authority.</p>
            <p>That ſome may fall from Truth's Principles, is too true; but that contending for the Form of it, is either a ſign they are fallen, or a means to make them fall, I muſt deny. If others have turned Perſecutors, its no wonder, becauſe the Principles upon which they ſtand, if well conſidered, do naturally lead them to Perſecution. And if any of them do not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, its either for want of Power, or they refrain in Policy, or eſle the natural goodneſs &amp; tenderneſs of their own Diſpoſitions over-power their Principles; for many mens natural Tempers are better than their Religions.</p>
            <p>But now, Truth has taught a little Flock ſuch peaceable Principles as deſtroy Perſecution Root and Branch. How is it poſſible he ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, that heartily believes, <hi>Every Religions Meeting ought to have liberty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61406:6"/>worſhip God according to their Conſciences?</hi> Can men deſire more <hi>Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? That its not lawful to hurt any mans Perſon, good Name, or Eſtate, for matters of Religion; and Conſcience towards God.</hi> Can civil Property be better ſecured from Perſecution? In brief, our Goſpel teaches our Hands to ſeed them that would ſtarve us; our Tongues to pray for them who curſe us. And the God of Peace, (glory to his Name) has brought this little Flock into his Lamb's Nature, the New Creature, that cannot kill, hurt, or do violence to any. And without this New Nature all Religion is but ſounding Braſs.</p>
            <p>Now if any man cannot be content with this Liberty, that is, to joyn himſelf to what Meeting beſt liketh him, but he will thruſt in for Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with us, and will exclaim againſt us as Perſecutors, if we will not let him have a liberty which we cannot take our ſelves; doth not ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Friend become rather a Perſecutor of us, than we of him? To force a liberty to break Order, and to force to conform to it, are <hi>Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> alike to be denyed.</p>
            <p>There is a caution neceſſary to mind, relating to theſe things. I have obſerved, that ſuch as oppoſe the Order of Truth, under pretence for Truth, do frequently in their writings and ſpeakings, call upon us, <hi>To keep to that which firſt convinced us.</hi> Good Counſel: Would they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were obedient to it. But they abuſe it, by applying it to a wrong end. For when they bid us keep to that which firſt convinced, and withal tell us of the bleſſed Appearance of the Lord among Friends in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, their ſence is, we ſhould keep to that Order and Diſcipline which was then among Friends: Which I grant to be good and ſuitable for that day and time: But by directing to that now, they ſecretly inſinuate a Reproof of what ever is more than was at firſt, as if ſet up by Man's Wiſdom, as <hi>Womens Meetings, Monethly, Quarterly</hi> and <hi>Yearly Meetings, our preſent Order of Marriage, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo, ſuch Friends as now walk in this Order, being thereunto led and guided by the ſame Spirit which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced them in the beginning, are by theſe pretending Friends, cryed down, as men of <hi>Form, Apoſtates, Innovators, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, to ſhew that this is their deſign and ſence, mark but the ſcope and drift of <hi>W. R</hi>'s Book againſt the <hi>Apoſtate Quaker</hi> (as he calls them) becauſe (in his meaning) fallen from what they were in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, which he dates to be about twenty ſix years then laſt paſt, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. 1ſt <hi>part</hi> But more briefly this may be ſeen in <hi>Anne Docwrays</hi> Paper, later printed, wherein there is ſome Rhyme, but not a word of Reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, that what ſhe ſcoffingly calls <hi>Formalities</hi> and <hi>Directories,</hi> have any Evils or Abſurdities in them. <hi>W. R.</hi> and <hi>She,</hi> exclaim much againſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61406:7"/>
               <hi>Impoſition,</hi> which we diſown more than they. But mark how ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, after many fine words againſt <hi>Forms, outward Rules, Contrivances, &amp;c.</hi> thus, <hi>[But God is bringing back again his People to their firſt Principles and Practice, whereby they were gathered into Community with him, and with one another in his Life and Power.]</hi> By this its as clear as the Sun, that ſhe miſapplies this Doctrine, as before noted.</p>
            <p>Many ſuch Inſtances might be given. Had this Woman lived in the Apoſtles days, might ſhe not as readily have charged them with <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> when they left oft having all things common, and ſet up Property among them? Might ſhe not have ſaid to <hi>Paul, —Keep to that which firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced thee, and tell not us of ordaining Elders or Overſeers in Churches,</hi> Tit. 15. 1 Tim. 3. <hi>Away with thy form of ſound Words,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.13. <hi>That Light which met thee going to</hi> Damaſcus, <hi>ſpake nothing then to thee of theſe things. Thou art now got into an aſpiring Mind, and ſeekeſt Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence over others. Thou art ſetting up Forms and Directories, outward Rules and Preſcriptions, which will be but Baits for the Enemy to with-draw mens Minds from the inward Teachings of the Grace of God into Contention.</hi> After this rate <hi>A. D.</hi> runs on in her Paper againſt the Truth of God now, which may as well be applied to the Primitive Times, as ours.</p>
            <p>But now, let us conſider, whether theſe who cry out ſo much of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy,</hi> are not themſelves the <hi>Apoſtates.</hi> Whom the Lord convinceth and converts, them he adds to his Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. Whom he adds to his Church, them he teaches to be obedient to the Diſcipline therein, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. This is plain Scripture. And the true Light in us, if we keep to it, will certainly ſatisfie us in the truth of this ſpiritual Rule and Government, and the ſtrength of it over our Spirits, we ſhall as ſenſibly feel, as outwardly we may feel the ſtrength of another mans Body over ours, by trying it. But as ſtubborn Bodies will not yield to ſtronger Bodies, though they dye for it; ſo ſtubborn forward Spirits will deſpiſe this ſpiritual Government, till they looſe their ſpiritual Life, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. A falſe Birth may cry, but not for the Breaſts. That which is born of God firſt breathes after him, and then after the Flocks of his Companions, Cant. 1.7. <hi>Tell me, O thou whom my Soul loveth, where thou feedeſt, where thou makeſt thy Flocks to reſt at Neon: For why ſhould I be as one that turneth aſide from the Flocks of thy Companious?</hi> Love to Chriſt, and to his Flock cannnot be ſeperated. So though I joyn to this Flock, its not becauſe they are a Flock, but becauſe they are Chriſt's Companions: And although I believe as they believe, yet I can faithfully ſay, its not becauſe they believe or practiſe this or that, but becauſe that Power, which brought me from the barren Mountains, (bleſſed be his Name)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61406:7"/>gave me the ſame Faith, and led me into the ſame fruitful Vallies, where they were feeding. So by this I know, and dare be bold in Truth to ſay, not to upbraid, but in Love to inform our Oppoſers, pretending Friend ſhip, That either they miſtook at firſt, their Opinions were not right-they took that for the Lords Anointing which was not, or elſe they are really fallen off, or to ſpeak moſt moderately, turned aſide from the Works of the Lord: Oh! that they may return with greater Zeal than ever, to ſerve the Truth in this their day, before eternal Night come over them! It is very ſad to ſee any, that were firſt, to be laſt, but more to feel them in danger to be loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> If any ſhould Reply, <hi>That our Meetings are fallen from their firſt Faith, and have ſet up Formalities, contrary to Scripture and Reaſon; and therefore its as lawful now for any one, as it was for</hi> Luther <hi>formerly, to oppoſe a whole Body, when ſo corrupted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Bleſſed be the Lord, this is not our caſe. I do not find, nor did I ever meet any impartial Friend, or friendly Man, that would ſay, Theſe our Oppoſers have proved any one of our Principles, or any part of our Order, guilty of any Errors or Evils, or any way contrary to Scripture or ſound Reaſon. Neither did I ever hear they propounded a better Order or Diſcipline. But the burden of all their Books and Papers I meet with, is either againſt particular Perſons, or for <hi>Liberty, Liberty,</hi> againſt <hi>Forms, Orders, outward Rules, &amp;c.</hi> which if they would ſpeak plain Engliſh, is as much as to ſay, We would have a Religion like the Earth in its <hi>Chaos,</hi> without Form, void of Order, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. We would be a Garden, but not incloſed, like that in <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12. We would be fellow Citizens with you, provided there may be no Walls or Gates about your City. We are for Salvation for Walls, in that ſence which allows no means of Salvation, though lawful and honeſt. We are for liberty of go in and out of the City, which way, and when we pleaſe. In ſhort, they ſay in effect, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, We would have liberty for every one to do what is right in his own Eyes. Thus ſtrange confuſed Notions have entred, under pretence of keeping to the Light within (a true Doctrine) and have deceived many, and will certainly devour their ſtrength una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, if they do not return ſpeedily to the Lord, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.9.</p>
            <p>I would not be ſuppoſed by writing this, to be more zealous for the Form, than for the Power of Godlineſs; my daily Watch is againſt it: And I pray God, I and all that love the Truth, may not only grow in Words to ſpeak for it, but alſo in unfeigned Love to the Brethren, and that the very Spirit of our Minds may daily feel ſtrength renewed to withſtand all the fiery Darts, and all the guilded Baits of the Enemy.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:61406:8"/>
            <p>I do in this matter, as the Apoſtles did about Faith and Works, and as all Chriſtians ought to do, <hi>viz.</hi> to countermine where we feel the Enemy undermining. When the <hi>Romans</hi> began (an early beginning) to be tainted with a Belief, That Works, without Faith, would ſave them; <hi>Paul</hi> zealouſly writes for Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. But when <hi>James</hi> perceived the ſcattered Tribes inclinable to err on the other hand, he writes as fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Works, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. So a concern is upon my Heart, to vindicate even the Form of Godlineſs, becauſe I feel the Serpent deſigning to bring us to Diſorder and Confuſion, under the fair pretences of Liberty, as before mentioned.</p>
            <p>And if it be true, as I heard one, (no ſmall Oppoſer, and for whom I greatly ſorrow) ſay, <hi>That the Worm which ſpoils the Shell, breeds in the Kernel;</hi> then there is much more cauſe to examine their Pretences to Power, than many apprehend. For by this Argument, all their talk of Power, and ſeeming Power, is to be ſuſpected as wrong, becauſe no Worm can breed in the true living Power of God, that will ſpoil the Shell or Form of Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> There is one thing more with me to add concerning Judgment: It hath ſometimes been returned upon me, in conference about theſe things, <hi>That I judged none to be Friends, by theſe Arguments, but ſuch as were conformable to our Order and Forms; and this was judging according to outward Appearances; and that I muſt not judge, leſt I be judged,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is thick Darkneſs in this Objection, eſpecially being made by one in ſome things conformable to Truth, whereby the World judges him to be a <hi>Quaker.</hi> Now he muſt either own or diſown this Judgment: If he own it, be contradicts himſelf, in ſaying, <hi>No judgment is to be made by outward Appearance:</hi> If he diſown it, he condemns himſelf of Hypocriſie, in appearing to be what he is not. But further, let ſuch pretending Friends, who thus object, conſider, whether they themſelves do not in their own Thoughts, daily, as they walk the ſtreets, make a judgment of People according to outward Appearances? I do not mean as to their eternal ſtate, but do they not judge ſuch to be no <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are dreſſed in the World's Faſhions? So by the ſame Rule as they judge them to be no <hi>Quakers,</hi> which have not the viſible dreſs or habit of <hi>Quakers,</hi> muſt they juſtifie me in judging them to be no Members of our Meetings, whoſe Behaviour there is not orderly and agreeable to our Principles. He is not of a right Spirit, who is not as watchful not to offend thoſe he pretends to own as a Church of Chriſt, as not to offend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>w or <hi>Gentile.</hi> And if he believe us not to be a Church of Chriſt, why
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61406:8"/>doth he frequent our Aſſembly, and there ſit, as in Unity with our Worſhip?</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>But what then is forbidden by theſe two Scriptures,</hi> Mat. 7.1. John 7.24?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1. Chriſt forbids <hi>judging ſo of others, as we would not be judged our ſelves.</hi> Wherefore he adds, <hi>For with what Judgment ye judge, ye ſhall be judged. He that judges without Mercy, ſhall have Judgment without Mercy.</hi> So this takes not away all, but only partial and unjuſt Judgment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>John</hi> 7.24. That judgment is forbid which the <hi>Jews</hi> made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the appearance of Letter of the Law. When the literal Sence or Letter, is a Figure, we muſt not judge by that ſence. The fore-going Verſes clear this: The <hi>Jews</hi> were angry becauſe Chriſt made a man whole on the Sabbath day: He convinced them, it was no Breach of their Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, by their own practice of Circumciſion upon that day, in caſe of neceſſity. For that day was but a Figure of future Reſt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.17. So it was made for Man, not Man for it; that is, it was to be ſubject to man, not man to it, <hi>Mark</hi> 2.27. And tho' the Letter of the Law was, <hi>In it thou ſhalt not do any Work;</hi> yet if they judged righteouſly, this did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid good Works, as neceſſity called for, as Circumciſion, or ſaving the Life of a Beaſt, themſelves being Judges, much more doing good to men. Wherefore he reproves them for judging after the Appearance or Letter of the Law, and not according to the Equity or Righteouſneſs of it in his caſe, as well as in their own. Great is that blindneſs and ignorance which wreſts theſe Scriptures, to ſilence all judging and condemning what in Truth ought to be judged and condemned.</p>
            <p>So I ſhall conclude, with referring to what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Bodies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. <hi>If any man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy.</hi> This Temple, in chap. 6.19. he expounds to be our Bodies. Now as the Body is a Temple for the Soul, ſo I own the Form to be but as a Temple for the Power. Yet if any man wound this living Temple, this living Form, the Life, Spirit and Power within it, will cry out, and teſtifie againſt him.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
